<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>analysis | Gauri Chaudhari</title>
    <link>https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/categories/analysis.html</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/categories/analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>analysis</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en</language><copyright>© 2024 Gauri Chaudhari</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>analysis</title>
      <link>https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/categories/analysis.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Visual Impact on New York&#39;s Creative Pulse</title>
      <link>https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/project/a-visual-impact-on-new-yorks-creative-pulse.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/project/a-visual-impact-on-new-yorks-creative-pulse.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Visual Impact on New York’s Creative Pulse encapsulates the essence of the city&amp;rsquo;s artistic reawakening, depicted through an innovative interactive dashboard fueled by the Guaranteed Income for Artists program. This visualization not only highlights the demographic diversity and narratives of New York&amp;rsquo;s artists but also brings to the forefront the profound interplay of identity, inclusivity, and artistic endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In crafting our interactive tableau data visualization, we relied on the Guaranteed Income dataset as our foundation. Our methodology was meticulous, prioritizing data integrity through extensive cleaning (especially on the geographical aspects) and preparation processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;approaches-performed-in-python&#34;&gt;Approaches performed in Python:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed Invalid Entries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparing geographical agttributes to outline the latitude and longitude&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Cleaning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;approaches-performed-in-excel&#34;&gt;Approaches performed in Excel:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our strategy in Excel involved disaggregating multi-response variables across separate sheets, linked via participant IDs.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This crucial step shifted our data from a wide to a long format, maintaining the integrity of each participant&amp;rsquo;s responses across multiple variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geographic data underwent a rigorous validation process, cross-referencing zip codes with a detailed lookup table to correct city names and ensure geographical accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;final-visualization-tableau-&#34;&gt;Final Visualization: tableau –&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We used &lt;strong&gt;calculated fields&lt;/strong&gt; to calculate KPIs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our map visualizations leveraged Tableau&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;dynamic zone visibility&lt;/strong&gt;, enabling users to drill down from regions to counties, and counties to cities with seamless interactivity.
a.	We made use of &lt;strong&gt;parameters&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;actions&lt;/strong&gt; in Tableau to create interactivity between region, county, and city maps
b. Simultaneously we can view the demographic information as well as the count of enrolled participants for the selected geographical area by hovering.
c.	For the hovering effect, we used &lt;strong&gt;viz in the tooltip&lt;/strong&gt;
d.	The end user can select from the &lt;strong&gt;demographic dropdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore the overall New York City nature of the applicants and for the variables that were multi-response we created a narrative of visualizations such as bubble charts, treemaps, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dashboard&#34;&gt;Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about the dashboard and to view the dashboard click on the tableau button at the top.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Housing Sales Analytics Dashboard</title>
      <link>https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/project/interactive-housing-sales-analytics-dashboard.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gaurichaudhari9.github.io/project/interactive-housing-sales-analytics-dashboard.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This dashboard visualizes and analyzes housing sales data for King County, Washington. The dashboard features a calendar widget, line chart, map, histograms, and a heatmap, providing a user-friendly interface to explore the dataset. The purpose is to understand trends in housing prices and identify relationships between price and other attributes like number of bedrooms/bathrooms, square footage, view, condition, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dashboard allows users to filter the data by month and day to see how prices change over time. Additional filters for year built, square feet living area, and square feet lot area allow further slicing of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis&#34;&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dashboard consists of the following visualizations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Line chart showing average price over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map showing average price by ZIP code, colored by price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Histogram showing distribution of house prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Histograms for distribution of number of bedrooms and bathrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heatmap showing average price by view and condition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visualizations allow us to identify trends like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prices increasing over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Areas with higher concentrations of expensive houses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most houses having 2-4 bedrooms and 1-3 bathrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher prices for better views and conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;instructions&#34;&gt;Instructions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dashboard can be filtered in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select month and day from calendar to filter all visualizations to that time period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use sliders for year built, square feet living area, and square feet lot area to filter the bottom 4 visualizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hover over marks in the visualizations to see more details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dashboard is interactive and allows slicing data in different ways to uncover insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dashboard&#34;&gt;Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about the dashboard click on the github icon at the top and to view the dashboard click on the tableau button at the top.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
